Women's Studies Task Force Collection, 1979-80
Smith College Archives
Women's Studies Task Force Collection
1979-1980
Women's Studies Task Force
RG 80 UUID:5738a073-015b-401d-b961-b277a4aaa78b
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Student Group. The Women's Studies Task Force was formed at a crucial time in the history of the development of women's studies at Smith College. The Task Force, like its parent organization, the Women's Resource Center, played an instrumental, if little recognized role in providing impetus towards a formal women's studies program at the College. The records include administrative records and research materials. The bulk of the collection is research material from the Interterm Project of the Women's Studies Task Force.
The Women's Studies Task Force, a student group, was formed as an operational group of the Women's Resource Center (WRC) in February, 1979. Faith Reidenbach, a member of the Center, served as the group's first chair, and other WRC members formed the bulk of the initial membership of the Task Force. In 1979, the Women's Resource Center (chartered by the College in 1973) supported three task forces, the other two being the ERA Task Force and the Health Task Force.
The Women's Studies Task Force was formed at a crucial time in the history of the development of women's studies at Smith College. The Task Force, like its parent organization, the WRC, played a vitally instrumental, if little recognized role in providing impetus towards a formal women's studies program at the College. The Task Force was formed under the 'pledge' of the WRC to "work with the CEP [Committee on Educational Policy] for as many years as it takes to persuade the administration to recognize a formal women's studies program" (WRC Newsletter, Feb. 16, 1979).
Prior to 1979, women's studies courses at Smith College, instituted formally by a CEP mandate in 1974, were integrated into the various traditional academic departments, for reasons both practical and philosophical (with the latter, much discussion in academia at the time centered around concerns that formal women's studies programs would 'ghetto-ize' women in the curriculum). With the arrival of Jill Ker Conway in 1975 as president, a focus on women's issues and needs in general, as well as within the College curriculum, gained attention and funding. In 1978, President Conway obtained the first of a series of significant grants from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation to form the Project on Women and Social Change, a multi-year research program. This project was funded in answer to a proposal for the creation of a women's studies research center as a part of the College, an idea that was resisted by the majority of the faculty and rejected by the faculty Committee on Research on the Study of Women.
Involved in this committee and in the Women and Social Change Project was Professor Marilyn Schuster of the French Department, also a member of the Committee to Review the Curriculum for the CEP. Professor Schuster was also a part of the initial meeting of the Women's Studies Task Force, as was Professor Susan Van Dyne of the English Department. Both professors acted as mentors to the group. In the spring of 1980, Professors Schuster and Van Dyne recommended, without success, the formation of an ad hoc or advisory committee on Women's Studies to the CEP and the Committee on Committees, with the support of the Women's Studies Task Force. No further records of Task Force activity beyond this time are apparent.
The matter of women's studies was taken up the next academic year by the Project on Women and Social Change Curriculum Group, for which Professor Schuster wrote proposals to coordinate the current women's courses through additional text in the handbook and in student advising. The Committee on Women's Studies was formed in 1982 following a renewed proposal by Professor Schuster and further action in November, 1982, by the WRC in the form of an 'open discussion' on options for women's studies in which both President Conway and Professor Schuster spoke, as well as other key faculty members. A minor in Women's Studies was instituted in 1984 and a major in 1987.
The Women's Studies Task Force's main accomplishment and contribution to the process of formalizing women's studies at Smith College was its research work, primarily accomplished during the Interterm Project it was awarded by the Student Government Association in January, 1980.
The Women's Studies Task Force records consist of 1 linear foot (2 boxes) and are the administrative records from 1979-80 and the records and research materials related to the Interterm Project of the Women's Studies Task Force conducted in January 1980. The bulk of the collection is research material from the Interterm Project. The research materials are divided into two sections--Smith College and Other-and date back to the early 1970's. There is no record of the disbandment of the group.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Administration
II. Interterm Project
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The records are open to public research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
History of the Collection
The Women's Studies Task Force Collection is composed in part from records transferred from the Sophia Smith Collection in the spring of 2003 and in part from donations to the College Archives by alumnae Deborah Levison, Class of 1982.
Search Terms
Smith College--Students.; Women's Studies Task Force (Smith College); Women--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Women's studies--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Women's Resource Center (Smith College)
Additional Information
Related Material
Further information on the Women's Studies Task Force may be found in the records of the Women's Resource Center and in an article entitled, "Women's Resource Center seeks to aid all women," in the April 16, 1979 edition of the Sophian. Related information pertaining to the Committee on the Study of Women can be found in the Dean of Faculty Office records and information on both the Women's Studies Committee and Women's Studies Program can be found in the Departmental records of the College Archives under the Women's Studies Program.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - Meeting minutes 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Studies Questionnaire undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meeting announcements ( Women's Resource Center newsletters) undated, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyer for Works in Progress program 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. INTERTERM PROJECT
  - Description and readings Jan., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Research
    - Smith College
      - Women's courses syllabi 1972-80 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Women's courses evaluations 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Women's courses statistics 1972-80 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Faculty and student research papers 1976-79 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Self-designed, interdisciplinary major by Jennifer Jackman, '82 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Jill Ker Conway articles 1974-79 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Women's Resource Center: publications 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Project on Women and Social Change 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Praxis (feminist publication) 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Freshman Colloquia 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Alumnae Quarterly (Kenneth McCartney article) Feb., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Other
      - UMass Women's Studies program 1977-81 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - National Women's Studies Association 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Women's Studies journals 1973-80 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Five College Women's Studies program 1976-81 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Bibliographies (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Research on women's studies and gender in the curriculum 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Project on the Status and Education of Women internship 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - General articles and publications on women (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Other women's studies programs descriptions and syllabi 1972-80 (Box 2, Folder 26)